Guide to the Herbert Whittaker Briggs legal papers, 1940-1986.
Briggs, Herbert Whittaker legal papers, 1940-1986.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Herbert Whittaker Briggs legal papers, 1940-1986.
18-2-2371
Herbert W. (Herbert Whittaker) Briggs, 1900-
31.5 cubic ft.
Correspondence, notes, maps, court transcripts, and other legal documents.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Background documents, court transcripts, other legal documents, notes, correspondence, and maps relating to cases in which Professor Briggs was involved or consulted.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Herbert Whittaker Briggs was Professor of government and international law at Cornell University.
The Barcelona Traction, Light and Power Company, Limited was a Canadian holding company incorporated in Toronto in 1911, which, through its various subsidiaries, supplied the major part of electricity requirements in Catalonia, Spain. The case was brought before the International Court of Justice for reparation for damage claimed to have been caused to a number of Belgian nationals, shareholders in the Barcelona Traction, Light and Power Company, by the conduct of various organs of the Spanish State in relation to that company and to other companies of its group.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Background documents, court transcripts, other legal documents, notes, correspondence, and maps relating to cases in which Professor Briggs was involved or consulted. Cases include the Barcelona Traction Company case, a border dispute between Honduras and Nicaragua, 1960; a dispute between Chile and Argentina over the interpretation of the Boundary Treaty of July 23, 1881 relating to the Beagle Channel, 1973-1975; two cases involving delimitation of the Contintental Shelf between Libya and Tunisia, ca. 1978-1981, and between Libya and Malta, ca. 1983-1986; a case between the United States and Canada over the delimitation of the maritime boundary in the Gulf of Maine area; arbitration between the United Kingdom and French governments on the delimitation of the Continental Shelf (in the English Channel). Also, working documents for the United Nations Conference on the Law of Treaties held in Vienna, 1968.
Also, material on the 1964 National Conference of Commissioners, New York State Commission of Uniform State Laws (1962), drafts of Uniform Commercial Code prior to 1952 and 1960, and preparation for introduction of the code in new York.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Briggs, Herbert W., 1900-; Barcelona Traction, Light, and Power Company.; International Court of Justice.; United Nations Conference on the Law of Treaties, Vienna, 1968-1969
Subjects:
International law.; Boundaries.; Treaties.
Places:
Belgium--Claims vs. Spain.; Honduras--Boundaries--Nicaragua.; Nicaragua--Boundaries--Honduras.; Beagle Channel (Argentina and Chile); Chile--Boundaries--Argentina.; Argentina--Boundaries--Chile.; Continental shelf--Libya.; Libya--Boundaries--Tunisia.; Libya--Boundaries--Malta.; Tunisia--Boundaries--Libya.; Malta--Boundaries--Libya.; United States--Boundaries--Canada.; United States--Boundaries--United States.; Continental shelf--Great Britain.; Great Britain--Boundaries--France.; France--Boundaries--Great Britain.
Form and Genre Terms:
Maps.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Documents on the arbitration between the United Kingdom and French governmentsare closed, subject to the decision ofthe United Kingdom and France, 67 rue Liotard, 1203 Geneva, Switzerland (the Court Registrar's address).
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Barcelona Traction case
  - Background documents, court transcripts, Reports of Judgments, and other International Court of Justice documents, 1953-1969 (Box 1)
  - Background and other documents, 1968-1969 (Box 2)
  - Judgments and separate opinions, 1970 (Box 2)
  - High Court of Justice Chancery Division documents, ca. 1967 (Box 3)
  - Public Sittings of the International Court of Justice, Apr.-June 1969 (Box 4)
  - Public Sittings of the International Court of Justice, June-July 1969 (Box 5)
  - Supreme Court of Ontario binders (photocopies of older documents) (Box 5)
  - Belgian case documents, 1959-1967 (Box 6)
  - Spanish case documents, 1960-1965 (Box 7)
  - Spanish case documents:
    - Preliminary exception folders, 1963 (Box 8)
    - "Documents of Exceptions ..." folders, 1963 (Box 8)
  - Spanish case documents, 1965-1968 (Box 9)
  - H.W. Briggs' files on Barcelona Traction Case (Box 10)
- Series II. Honduras v. Nicaragua border dispute, 1960
  - Consultations, oral pleadings, and correspondence (Box 10)
- Series III. Beagle Channel arbitration between Argentina and Chile
  - Background information, bound court documents, typescript copies of court hearings, notes and correspondence (Box 11-13)
  - Atlas: Chilean Memorial, 1973 (Box 11-13)
  - Atlas: Chilean Counter-Memorial, 1974 (Box 11-13)
  - Atlas: Chilean Reply, 1975 (Box 11-13)
  - Counter Memorial of the Argentine Republic: Charts and Maps I, 1974 (Box 11-13)
  - Counter Memorial of the Argentine Republic: Charts and Maps II, 1975 (Box 11-13)
  - Reply of the Argentine Republic: Charts and Maps, 1975 (Box 11-13)
- Series IV. Libyan Continental Shelf cases
  - Libya v. Tunisia
    - Libya v. Tunisia dispute over land boundary on the Continental shelf includes bound court documents, oral proceedings, maps, ca. 1978-1981 (Box 14-16)
  - Libya v. Malta
    - Libya v. Malta court documents, correspondence, maps, ca. 1983-1986 (Box 16-18)
    - Maps (Box 19)
    - Maps (Box 20)
    - H.W. Briggs' files on both cases (Box 21)
- Series V. U.S. vs. Canada - Gulf of Maine case
  - Briggs' files on the delimitation of the maritime boundary in the Gulf of Maine area (Box 21-22)
  - Maps (Box 21-22)
- Series VI. Vienna Conference of the Law of Treaties
  - Working documents for the 1968 U.N. conference (Box 22-23)
- Series VII. Arbitration between the United Kingdom and French governments on the delimitation of the Continental shelf, 1975-1978
  - Court documents and background information (RESTRICTED) (Box 24-25)
  - Maps (RESTRICTED) (Box 24-25)
  - "The Attorney General Invokes Rebus Sic Stantibus", 1941-1942 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Barcelona Traction, Light and Power Ltd., "Annals of Finance" - New Yorker, May 28, 1979, 1971, 1979 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Beagle Channel Arbitration - Award of Her Britannic Majesty's Government, 1977 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Beagle Channel Arbitration between the Republic of Argentina and the Republic of Chile - maps (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Barcelona Traction, Light and Power Company, Limited (Second Phase) Judgment, 1970 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Continental Shelf - Arbitration between the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland and the French Republic on the Delimitation of the Continental Shelf, 1978 (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - "Case Concerning the Continental Shelf (Tunisia/Libya Arab Jamahiriya)", 1982 (Box 26, Folder 7-10)
  - "Case Concerning the Continental Shelf (Libyan Arab Jamahiriya/Malta)" - judgment, 1985 (Box 26, Folder 11)
  - Case Concerning the Continental Shelf (Libyan Arab Jamahiriya/Malta), Application for Permission to Intervene by the Government of Italy International Court of Justice, 1984 (Box 26, Folder 12)
  - Debate on Neutrality and Destroyer Deal, 1940 (Box 26, Folder 13)
  - Debate on Neutrality and Destroyer Deal - Sale of U.S. Destroyers to England, 1940 (Box 26, Folder 14)
  - (Campus) Debate on Neutrality - Briggs and Willcox - "Neglected Aspects of the Destroyer Deal (see also International Law), 1940 (Box 26, Folder 15)
  - International Court of Justice Study Group (Paris-Bellagio-Serbelloni), 1960-1961 (Box 26, Folder 16-19)
  - International Court of Justice Study Group (C) Bellagio, Villa Serbelloni, 1963 (Box 26, Folder 20)
  - International Court of Justice Study Group, 1963 (Box 27, Folder 1-2)
  - International Law Survey, Report on, ca. 1962 (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - International Law Survey Journal Notes Europe - Africa - Asia, 1961 (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - International Law Survey Journal Notes Latin America, 1962 (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - International Law Commission - 1961 Election, 1961 (Box 27, Folder 6-7)
  - International Law Commission - nomination and correspondence, 1954, 1961-1966 (Box 27, Folder 8-9)
  - International Law Commission Drafting Committee, 1963-1965 (Box 27, Folder 10-12)
  - International Law Commission Drafting Committee, 1966 (Box 27, Folder 13-15)
  - International Law Commission Drafting Committee - Arbitration Agreement United Kingdom and French Republic, 1975 (Box 27, Folder 16)
  - Institut de Droit International - Communications from Secretary General, 1956-1985 (Box 27, Folder 17-19)
  - "Non-recognition in the Courts: T he Ships of the Baltic Republics", American Journal of International Law reprint, 1943 (Box 27, Folder 20)
  - Reports written by Briggs, 1947-1958 (Box 27, Folder 21-22)
  - "Re-examination of International Law" -American Journal International Law reprint, 1942 (Box 27, Folder 23)
  - Saudi Arabia and the Arabian American Oil Company (Aramco), Arbitration between, 1959, 1966 (Box 27, Folder 24)
  - UN Conference on the Law of Treaties, Vienna - mss. and notes of Briggs' speeches, 1968 (Box 27, Folder 25-28)
  - "United States and Post-War International Organization" in The Impact of the War on America (Cornell Press), 1942 (Box 27, Folder 29)
  - "The Validity of the Greenland Agreement" (Box 27, Folder 30)
  - Arbitral Award Made by the King of Spain, 1906, Oral Proceedings, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Arbitral Award Made by the King of Spain (Honduras v. Nicaragua), 1960 (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - Beagle Channel Arbitration Decision, 1977 (Box 28, Folder 3-6)
  - Delimitation of the Maritime Boundary in the Gulf of Maine Area (Canada v. U.S.A.), 1984 (Box 28, Folder 7)
  - Volumes:
    - Beagle Channel Arbitration, Chilean Memorial, ATLAS, 1973 (Box 28)
    - ATLAS, Chilean Counter-Memorial, Beagle Channel Arbitration, 1974 (Box 28)
    - Argentine Chilean Arbitration concerning the Region of the Beagle Channel, Counter Memorial of the Argentine Republic, Charts and Maps, vol. I, 1974 (Box 28)
    - Argentine Chilean Arbitration concerning the Region of the Beagle Channel, Counter Memorial of the Argentine Republic, Charts and Maps, vol. II, 1974 (Box 28)
    - Argentine Chilean Arbitration concerning the Region of the Beagle Channel, Reply of the Argentine Republic, Charts and Maps, 1975 (Box 28)
    - ATLAS, Chilean Reply, Beagle Channel Arbitration, 1975 (Box 28)